hello it's keith here and this is lesson
seven of the platform specific series of
my pdp-11 assembly programming tutorials
we're looking at the uknc again and i've
got an oscilloscope above me again which
should tell you i'm probably doing
something involving sound so we're going
to be writing my chibi sound driver on
the uknc chibi sound is a very simple
sound driver that i write on all of
these systems and it allows me to make
simple beeps in my games in a sort of
similar way in all of the systems which
reduces the amount of time it takes me
to board games and gives me less of a
headache when i'm trying to remember all
of the different systems i'm programming
so what does chibi sound do well it
takes a single byte and typically what
it will do is it will use six bits to
define a pitch it will take one bit to
define whether the noise is on or off
and it will take one bit to define the
volume level now the uknc is of
basically a beeper speaker very much
like the spectrum where we have one bit
to create a waveform this flips the
waveform and by repeatedly changing it
we can make high pitch and low pitch
sounds and if we change it a bit
randomly it'll make distorted sounds
however to my knowledge there's no way
we can really change the volume so we're
not going to be changing the volume in
the tv sound driver today so the volume
is always going to be loud so that is
going to be the limitation today now the
code today is very different to the
spectrum code though the spectrum
version um even though the beeper's
function is very similar the spectrum
version would make a sound for a short
period and then return to the calling
routine whereas on the uknc the uk has
two processors and it's only the ppu the
subprocess the peripheral processor that
can actually make a sound so instead of
returning after making a short beep what
we're going to do is we're going to make
a constant beep on that subprocessor
this gives us the advantage of constant
sound the disadvantage is though
if we have that process of making a
sound all the time it can't be doing
anything else and so that's going to
disable the core functionality of the
ppu and it's going to stop responding to
most of the calls from the main cpu now
the exception to that is um i've written
a little game called um stop shoot which
is a little simple batch shooting game
my keyboard driver that we covered in
the previous example in the platform
series that is interrupt based so that
is not affected by the um sound driver
but the um the main code
that would handle the console simulation
i believe is now there's probably a way
of creating an interrupt driven sound
driver i i haven't written one here it's
not that advanced but it will at least
work in a basic way so let's first up
fire up the example and let's hear it in
action not see it in action for a change
so here you can hear that we've got a
high pitch and it's getting lower as the
value goes up i'm not showing it to the
screen the value because the console
doesn't work
and then
we will get some distortion sounds here
there's some distortion
now you'll notice that the waveform's a
bit erratic there that's why it's
distorted but generally
the tighter the waveform the higher the
frequency the higher the pitch the
larger the distance between the waves
the um
larger the wavelength the lower the
pitch
anyway
let's go over to the code and let's take
a look
okay so what is our code doing well
first of all let's see what we're
actually having to do to get the sound
example working now what we're doing is
we are basically
taking our
tv sound driver and we're sending it to
the sub cpu and we're executing on the
sub cpu but unlike previous examples
we're not returning once it completes
because it doesn't actually complete it
will keep making the sound keep waiting
for more data for sounds to make so that
is going on forever
so once our driver is enabled we're then
returning and we're changing this byte c
sound a which is the byte parameter that
we're passing
in the format that chibi sound usually
takes so the bottom six bits are the
pitch
high value is a high pitch a low value
is low pitch and then if bit 7 is set
then we end up with a noise sound the
the volume
bit is ignored but the sound off does
where it did work so if we send a zero
value that will turn off this will
silence the sound now the this version
of the driver takes a second byte and
this is the b byte and if this is
non-zero it will actually terminate the
running driver the reason for this is as
i said that sub cpu is not functioning
properly and we are trying to send
characters to that term sub cpu to show
to the screen
but lo and behold nothing is appearing
on the screen and that's because the
chibi sound driver is in the way and
it's stopping anything else running now
if we set that b byte to a non-zero
value this will actually terminate chibi
sound and then this is actually
uninstalling the chibi sound sub routine
freeing up the memory from the sub cpu
so if we run this again
we will get
a short beep and then those characters
are now showing to the screen and they
were being sent before but they weren't
showing because the sub cpu was still
running chibi sound so if we just want a
short beat we can execute it and then
tell it to return if we want a constant
beep though or we need it running on the
sub cpu and as i say we're going to have
to deal with our graphics functionality
and our keyboard reading functionality
in some other kind of way because that
sub cpu is going to be fully occupied by
chibi sound so let's see what chibi
sound is actually doing well first of
all we've got two bytes on the main cpus
memory here that we are using to pass
the tubie sound and like before we are
calculating the address and we of of
those bytes we're dividing by two and
then passing it to the wrap port that's
how we access memory on the main cpu
from the sub cpu so it's the sub cpu
running this code now
we are going to need in some cases some
random data and we don't really have a
random source so what we're using is
we're using part of the rom cartridge
we're using the b triple zero to d
triple zero range in hexadecimal and
that's fairly random it gives a kind of
random distorted sound and so we're
loading that address range in r2 and
we're going to sequence through that as
a random source when we want random data
so what we're doing here is we're moving
a byte from
177014 into r0 that is our parameter
from chibi sound which is the pitch and
whether the noise is on or off and what
we're going to do here is we're going to
check the noise bit
and we're going to see if the noise is
on or not now if the noise is off we're
going to set r3 to be with the top bit
set to one
otherwise we're going to set it to zero
why are we doing this well it's the top
bit that actually controls the speaker
and we need to use port one triple seven
one six in octal on the sub cpu not on
the main cpu only on the sub cpu and
this will toggle the wave so we need to
create a wave it'll be a square wave
like that and every time we write to
that port we are basically toggling from
one direction to the other and the speed
we toggle will change the pitch and if
we change it a bit randomly that will
create a distorted sound now
if we want a constant tone we always
want to toggle with a value of one in
that bit which is why if noise is off we
are setting the bit seven to one here
that's what moving that octal 200 to r3
is doing otherwise we want a random
value and we are going to get that from
r2
so what we're doing here
is we are loading a value of 200 into r1
we're possibly clearing the bit
depending on our random data in our two
and then we're setting the bit from r3
and so basically r one will either
contain a top bit of one or zero
depending on whether the noise is set
and we're xoring that with the port one
triple seven one six that is effectively
toggling our waveform that xor is doing
it but the value in r1 to say it needs
to be a constant one in that top bit if
we want a constant tone or it needs to
alternate if we need a random tone now
that's how we're toggling the waveform
and how we're handling the noise but we
also need to handle the pitch now the
way we handle the pitch is simply that
we wait a certain period before we flip
that bit again and we've got that in r0
we've basically loaded in our zero from
our parameter byte that was passed to us
and we've cleared all but the zero to 63
range using this bit clear here and
we're just shifting it to the left by
three bits to give it the correct range
for the kind of pictures that we want
now
we are just basically waiting here doing
nothing not changing anything in the
sound hardware and then what we're going
to do is basically loop back up and
we're going to flip the bit again and
that will create our waveform but
there's a few other jobs we're going to
do first the first one we're going to do
is we're going to test the second byte
which is the c sound b byte which is
used to terminate the command so we're
going to check if that is set and if it
is set we're going to terminate chibi
sound we're going to set the finished
flag and this is used by our calling
routine to free up the memory and then
we're going to return
but if the terminate command isn't set
then the only thing would left to do is
to make sure that the random data source
in r2 is not at the end of the wrong
range that is a good tone now if we go
too high we'll actually end up with the
memory map registers and if we start
reading from those anything could happen
we don't want to do that that could
crash things and other ranges will have
zeros in them which won't create noise
samples that are very good so as i say
we're limiting r2 to this fixed range
there but basically once we've got to
this point we're just jumping straight
back to the top and we're repeating the
whole procedure testing the chibi sound
bytes seeing if it's zero if it is zero
we're doing nothing otherwise we're
making the sound again and this is
creating the tones so there we go so
that's how we can create sound on this
system it's pretty straightforward so if
you've liked what you've seen please
like and subscribe because if you like
the videos youtube recommends more to be
to more people and if you subscribe i
get happy and i make more videos so it's
good for everyone anyway as i say go to
the website download the source code and
build scripts for today's example and
you can have a go with it and maybe have
some fun with it and use it in any way
you can benefit from anyway i hope
you've enjoyed what you've seen today
thanks for watching and goodbye