hello it's keith here and this is lesson
one of the simple series of my pdp 11
assembly programming tutorials we're
looking at a simple example today and
we're going to go over pretty much all
of the source code because a lot of the
previous examples i've been doing
recently on the pdp-11 uknc is uh we've
not really covered the entire code and
i've said i'll go back to this example
and i've covered that before we're going
to go over all of the code give or take
today and discuss each of the sections
that have been required to make today's
example and today's example is a smiley
face moving around the screen of the uk
and see you can see we've got this
little smiley here we can move it around
the screen and it cannot go off the
screen so we've got some range checking
keyboard reading and we've got our
screen setup now the example today we're
using the um sub cpu to do the keyboard
reading but we've actually remapped the
video memory to the main cpu so that the
final code can actually all run from the
main cpu the problem with this is is it
means there's quite a few stages of
setup we have to reset the screen memory
up and we have to set up the keyboard
reader on the interrupt handler and so
we're going to see how all of that works
today
if you want to know how to create the
bitmap graphic the smiley was edited in
accurate spot edit in my free sprite
editor and if we go to pdb11 uknc we
have saved with the two-bit plane option
today this one here that is the version
we're using because the graphic is
effectively on the final screen of four
color graphic as i say the main cpu that
can only have two of the bit planes
mapped to it the third one is always
back mapped to the sub cpu so that is
why we're using four color graphic today
and we've got some simple range checking
to make sure our smiley can't go off the
screen okay well let's go over to the
source code the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to discuss the
basics of the code that is actually
doing the keyboard reading and moving
the smiley around and the reason for
this is assuming that you don't really
care how the background stuff setting
things up works which is going to be
easier for you and then we'll go into
the details of those rather difficult
setup so let's go to the code and let's
check it out okay
so here's our program our program is
starting at the beginning of pdp-11
memory here is our start routine here
and the first thing we're doing is we're
initializing the screen display with
this init routine that is setting up the
screen which is 320 by 240 four colors
within the main cpu memory there is a
one remaining midplane on the sub cpu
we're then installing our keyboard
driver here which is reading in the
keyboard that's an interrupt handler
which will set a 16 bit value with any
key presses that occur
during this main loop r1 and r2 are the
x and y position of our players smiley
we have a routine called show p which
will show the players smiley to the
screen this is an xor routine and what
this means is if we show the sprite
twice at the same position the second
time we'll invert it and effectively
remove it if it's drawn to the same
position twice
so cool p will show the player we then
have a delay and we're calling show p
again to the same position which will
remove it what we're then doing is we're
reading in the value from the keyboard
now the keyboard routine i'm using today
is the one we discussed in the platform
series last time this has two parts one
is it reaching the raw data and the
other is it will you do an a simulated
joystick it decodes the key presses and
converts them into an up down left right
fire one five two five three and pause
sequence and so we can then test those
bits for our up down left and right and
we're doing that with the bit command
which is effectively like an and command
that doesn't alter the register so that
will set the flags according to bits so
here we're testing bit zero that one is
testing bit zero here and if up is not
pressed in other words if that bit is a
one then we're skipping over the next
section we skip down to here if up is
pressed though we're going to check the
x and y coordinates now we need to check
the y coordinate in this case and if
we're trying to get up the screen we
need to check we're not already at
position zero and if we are we skip over
because we're already at the top of the
screen but if we're not we are
effectively adding um 10 in octal that's
18 decimal of course and so that is
moving as one block up the screen
we're moving in eight pixel blocks up
and down to match the movement speed of
left and right because we're moving in
bit plane bytes so that is eight pixels
effectively left and right so that's up
we're then doing the same with down here
we're testing bit one which is has a
value of two so we're doing a bit of two
which is effectively an end of two and
again we're going to skip over if down
is not pressed but if it is pressed
we're checking for the bottom of the
screen here and so we're testing for our
two four three lines tall screen here
and we are just seeing if we're already
at the bottom of the screen and if we're
not we're moving down the screen we're
then doing the same for left and right
here again same procedure this time just
using the register r1 which is our x
position as opposed to r2 which is our y
position and that is effectively moving
our player around the screen while
checking the range and we've just got a
restart to the infinite loop here which
is just showing the new position of the
player
we've got a vey crude pause routine here
which just decreases our zero until it
reaches zero very very basic there the
show p routine here is the routine that
actually shows our sprite to the screen
okay how do we do this well what we're
doing here is we're calculating our vram
destination here in decimal our formula
is 32768 which is the vram base of the
screen
plus 80 times the y position each line
is 40 blocks wide 848 pixel blocks wide
but each of those blocks takes two bytes
so that's times 80. and then our x
position times two because there are two
blocks for the two bit planes for each x
position
so that is our calculation in octal it's
this and you can see that represented in
here
here we're getting the y position
multiplying by octal 120 and that is
then having that value there that's a
hundred thousand i believe added to it
in octal that is the vram base that's
the start of our screen memory we're
then effectively doubling the x position
by shifting it to the left by one bit
and then adding that as well so r1 now
contains the vram destination of the
smiley for the position we want to show
it to
okay
now we are loading the address of our
sprite into r4 and we're loading the
height of our sprite into r5 here now
this routine has been based on one that
was designed to work with larger sprites
and i've kept that functionality in so
we've actually got a loop even though it
aspect is only one byte wide here so
that's why that's doing that unnecessary
thing so we're then just backing up the
address of the destination for this line
into our three we're moving a word out
of our four the source and we're
excelling at with the screen in r3 so
that is moving the two bit planes for
one byte block one eight pixel block
exerting it with the screen inverting
the screen with that value meaning as i
say if we draw it twice it will
disappear the second time well we're
repeating for any of the horizontal
blocks but actually there aren't any in
this example but as i say if you were
using a bigger sprite you would want a
wider value high value there we are then
moving down one line adding 80 in
decimal here moving us down one line
and then we are repeating so that is how
we are drawing all of the lines of our
smiley sprite now we've got our test
keyboard value here this is the value
that has been read in from the keyboard
interrupt handle the interrupt handler
will automatically set that and it's the
second byte that we want to read in for
the joystick simulation if we wanted raw
data which is a bit harder we would use
the first bite
here is our smiley sprite so our sprite
is eight lines so you can see there's
eight lines here and there are two bit
planes for each line each eight pixel
block is a single byte but then for this
for the four colors there are two bytes
so basically the first one of these is
the first bit plane and you can see
that's mostly set because that's for
color one but then if we want color two
or color three we need to set the second
book plane which you can see is rarely
used it's used basically for the smiling
the eyes so you can see that there
okay so that's our smiley there as i say
you can create your own with accurate
sprite edit or if you want to you can
create it in more numeric values and
that's the basics of our routine for
actually moving our smiley around the
screen so that's the part you would want
to modify if you were making your own
game and you didn't want to worry about
the screen setup or how to read in the
keyboard well what if you want to know
about that well okay brace yourself
because we're going to cover that right
now
so the fundamentals are the send command
routine what we have to do is we have to
transfer a command to the sub cpu and
execute it on the sub cpu we need to do
that if we want to install an interrupt
handler if we want to define a screen
layout things like that
now we have this sequence of data here
it's a little bit complicated but this
is in a fixed format which is the
correct format for instigating a command
on the sub cpu so the sub cpu has its
own operating system and we have to give
it data in the correct format that it
will understand and that's what we're
doing there
now one thing you do need to know about
is this flag end byte here yeah this is
a 16-bit value sorry now what this is um
this is a value on the main cpu but the
sub cpu can access main cpu memory via a
device known as the wrap device and so
what the sub cpu does is it's doing its
little job when it finishes its job it
alters this byte on the main cpu's
memory so that the main cpu knows the
sub cpu is finished so that we will see
in part of this code okay
so at the start of our routine here
we're just going to go over this in a
very simple way because it's it's really
too complicated and um it's kind of one
of the things if you if you can't
if you can't pick it apart yourself
which i would understand then you
probably just want to leave it alone and
use it as is so what we're doing here is
we are clearing the flag at the start
we're then setting up the kind of
request we're making and what we're
requesting is we're requesting the sub
cpu allocator some memory and we're then
running this routine called ppu out now
ppu out is the command that actually
sends a sequence of data to the sub cpu
because we're actually going to do
multiple tasks first we need to actually
allocate some memory then we need to
transfer our program then we need to
execute our program and then we want to
in this case release the memory so we're
doing all of these these are all tasks
with this ppu out they just have
different kinds of requests the request
will change each time you can see that
it's 30 there is 20 and so on and some
of the parameters will change
accordingly
okay so how do we actually transfer our
command well what we're doing here is we
are transferring the ps parameters we're
loading the address into r0
we're loading the number of bytes here
eight bytes in decimal
and we are transferring one byte
from r0 which is the parameters to the
port one seven six six seven six which
is channel two to the sub cpu we
transfer one byte and then we wait for
that byte to be processed by testing one
seven six six seven four and when that
is complete
completed when the data has been read by
the sub cpu we send the next byte and we
repeat until we're done
okay so the first request is an allocate
memory request and when that comes back
the memory that is available to us has
been allocated and we're storing that in
r5 for later the next one is that we
want to transfer our program from the
main cpu to the sub cpu
then we want to actually execute the
program on the sub cpu
we then wait for the flag end to change
which will change because the last
command of our program on running on the
sub cpu will change it
and then we release the memory that was
allocated and that is the procedure for
all of the examples here of when we're
running a program on the sub cpu okay
now the first program we're running is
the init routine here and you can see
there's some rather huge documentation
there on the memory layout of the vram
and we're really not going to cover this
in detail it's extremely complicated i'm
only going to give a very very brief
overview of what we're doing here
so we've got an init routine here which
will set up this screen memory and the
main reason we're doing this is normally
the video memory can only be accessed
via the wrap device and that's very slow
so
so that we've got something easier we're
reallocating the memory so that it's
within the addressable range or from the
main
cpu okay so the first thing we're doing
here is we are patching in the address
for our scan line table the scan line
table defines the layout of the screen
one line at a time
on the sub cpu this is defined by memory
address 272 in octal and we're actually
defining the scan line table at memory
just 4 000 in oxford so we're
transferring that memory address to 272
and that defines our custom scan line
table will be used we're then loading in
the destination vram of the first line
of a scanlan table though it should be
noted the first few lines aren't
actually visible on the screen okay
so what we're going to do is we're going
to use some special commands each line
of the scanline table can do different
tasks it can define just a line as raw
data but it can also change the memory
layout to change the screen resolution
change the colors and things like that
so you can do clever things like have
the palette change at different lines of
the screen quite complicated but quite
clever we're not going to do that today
though all we're going to do is we're
going to first set up the screen to be
320 pixels wide as opposed to 640. we're
then going to set our initial colors
here so we've got these little
subroutines that are going to do these
kind of jobs
and boy are they complicated which is
why we're not going to go over them in
great detail here so basically you can
see those lines here which are doing the
job of actually setting up things here
and so
here you can see we're setting this is a
line to set up the scale this is a line
to set up the color so if you want to
change the palette you would want to
change this line if you wanted to change
the resolution you'd want to change this
line but these are setting up valid data
format lines within the scan line table
so first we're setting the resolution
then we're setting up the palette and
then what we're doing here is we're
setting up 32 lines which are actually
invisible and we're so we're setting up
s to stab f here and this is to create
filler lines and basically all this is
doing is creating a sequence of lines
all of which point to the same vram
address because they're not actually
going to show any of the screen data
it's just filler so we're creating 32 of
those in decimal here and then we're
going to create the main body of the
screen and the main body of the screen
is showing memory address 40 000 in
octal 30 000 was for the top of the
screen but as i say that isn't actually
going to change that's just the black
border at the top of the screen
so
the vram for the actual visible screen
is 40 000 in octal although it should be
noted that this is the memory address
for the scanline table the actual memory
address that that memory appears in the
cpu is different so as i say we you will
see a different memory address in our
calculations for the vram destination
because of that
and we're creating 240 lines of the
actual main body of our screen and then
finally we're defining a an end of the
screen and looping back to the start of
the screen
now once we've defined our
screen layout in this case but any time
we've done a job on the subcpu we need
to send a complete command back to the
main cpu and we do this via the wrap
device this is a device that can write
any of the memory and in this case we
want to tell the main cpus memory that
the job is done now we select the memory
address to write to in with port
177010 and we need to calculate the vram
address for flag end but because the
main cpu's memory is actually two banks
interlaced together movement alternating
bytes we divide the memory address by
two for the calculated address that the
wrap will want to alter that byte and
we're then writing the value minus one
to
those memory bytes and so we write that
value to 177014
and that will set flag end to negative
in the main cpu memory
telling the main cpu that the job is
done and then the main cpu will release
the memory and so on
okay so that's how we're setting up our
vram at the start of our program so
that's that command there that sets up
the screen what about the key command
well we're going to cover this as well
we will cover it a little bit quickly
but we'll go into some detail
okay so we are going to set up our own
interrupt handler called key handle now
we're having to calculate this relative
to the current running line count
because we don't actually know the
memory address this will end up
executing from because it's going to be
transferred to allocated memory on the
sub cpu now the current line number can
be got from by using the full stop
symbol here so key handle minus dot is
calculating a relative address in the
code and we're then editing that to the
program counter when this is running on
the sub cpu so that will calculate the
correct address for the key handle of
once this program's finally running on
the sub cpu and what we're doing is
we're installing that interrupt handler
on the sub cpu by transferring that
address to memory address 300 which is
the interrupt handler address
that means that the keyhandler interrupt
handler will run on the sub cpu every
time a key is pressed we're then
setting the flag end and we're actually
returning that is actually the end of
the program because all of the rest of
the job is going to be done when the
interrupt occurs okay so when the
interrupt occurs key handle will execute
automatically on the sub cpu we need to
backup some registers and we need to
back up the wrapper drive address as
well because the wrapper device is being
used by the operating system but we're
going to use it to store the keys that
have been pressed so we are getting the
current key that has been pressed by
using one triple seven o2
that's the current key press and then
what we're going to do is we're then
going to actually process that key press
now the format of the key presses is a
little bit odd and slightly annoying but
it is um it's perfectly usable just a
little bit annoying so basically we have
a series of key presses depending on the
keys we want to read and we're going to
read the cursor keys primarily here when
a key is pressed down the top bit will
be zero and the other seven bits will be
the key code when a key is released the
top bit will be one the next three bits
will be zero and we will get a partial
keyboard code in the bottom four bits so
we don't get the full key code
now what we're going to do is we're
going to test the top bit
if the top bit is one then the minus
flag will be set and so we're going to
jump to this key up routine here
otherwise we're going to jump to this
key
down routine here just after that branch
minus and what this is going to do is
it's going to test a key map these are
the key presses for our keys up down
left right space enter shift and escape
that's the eight key presses that will
make up eight bits of the returned byte
and so we're simulating a kind of
joystick here
so if you wanted to change the direction
keys or something you would change these
key codes here and hopefully you don't
need to actually change the routine
so what the routine is doing here is
it's loading in a byte from that lookup
table here and it's repeating until it
either finds a key press or is done if
the key matches then what is happening
is we are clearing the bits that match
the um second byte of the key code so
for example if the key code was 154 then
the key up has been pressed and we would
want to clear bit zero and we would do
that by doing a bit clear with the value
one and so this is assuming that an
unpressed key will have a value of two
five five and a press key will have a
value of zero for its bit and so that's
what we're doing here so we are just
repeatedly looking through skipping over
the um that mask for the keys that
aren't pressed when we find a key that
is pressed we're clearing the bits and
we're doing that by transferring to the
wrap address the the wrap device second
byte address at
177015 and that will set the second byte
of the key test value in the main cpu
memory and so that is setting those
joystick values of simulated joystick
values that we were reading before when
a key is pressed down we are comparing
to the entire byte reading from that um
that keep keymap table there the entire
bike but when a key is up the routine is
different
first we're clearing the top bit of the
parameter that we read in because the
top bit is denoting the key up itself
and then what we're doing is we're
reading the bytes as before from the
lookup table of the key map but because
only four of the bits are actually set
by the key up we're clearing the
remaining bits here and we are then
comparing to the
the value that was been read in by the
interrupt handler so that's the key
press value and if the value matches
then we are setting the bits effectively
setting that bit the bit of that
direction to one but because multiple
things could match because we've only
got a partial key code we're keeping on
scanning until we get to the double zero
byte at the end and so that's what we're
doing there now when a match is found
we're setting the bits effectively
setting those to one here
and that is the keypress routine now as
i say all of that is unfortunately a
little bit complicated because of the
split cpu layout we've got two cpus and
that does mean that um things are a
little bit complicated but let's say
that's the example today and as i always
say you can go to my website download
the source code the build scripts and
you're welcome to use my example in any
way you want them the um
parts of the code for the um controlling
the sub cpu were written by someone else
i found them online so i can't take
credit for it all and i had a lot of
help with the scanline table information
because the original was in russian and
so part of that is i got all this the
information for free and so you're
welcome to use it in the same way in any
way you want to have fun with it and
have make some make something
interesting with it anyway hope you
enjoyed what you've seen today thanks
for watching and goodbye